now watch this his death leads us
away from the house of bondage
remember what egypt represents the house
of bondage
all the way to exodus chapter 11 you
have a series of miracles
and then in exodus 12 this is where the
passover takes place
the lord spake unto moses and aaron in
the land of egypt saying
this month shall be unto you the
beginning of
months it shall be the first month of
the year to you
so in other words what god is telling
the children of israel it is going
to mark a new
beginning for you this is to mark
new time for you children of israel
you're going to forget about old times
they are about to be delivered from
egypt but i want you to notice what it
says in exodus chapter 13 verse 3
and moses said unto the people remember
this day
in which you came out of egypt out of
the
house of bondage
egypt is synonymous with the house of
bondage so let's put that together god
is saying this
passover marks a new beginning for you
it marks new time you're gonna forget
about old times
old time i'm going to deliver you
from the house of bondage
if you're with me so far give me
something
now they leave egypt and i want you to
watch what happened next because the
bible says in exodus chapter 14
and verse 3 pharaoh
decides to go back after the children of
israel
okay he's going after them because he
doesn't want them to experience
new time he doesn't want them to
experience
new times he's going to go after them
and i want you to know what it says
exodus 14 3 for pharaoh will save the
children of israel
they are entangled in the land
okay i want you i have that word
highlighted in yellow because i want you
to remember that word
entangled pharaoh is hoping that they
will get entangled
so that he can draw them back to egypt
back to the house of bondage it goes on
to say
they are entangled in the wilderness and
the wilderness has shut them in
and i will harden pharaoh's heart that
he shall follow after them
and i will be honored upon pharaoh and
upon all his hosts
that the egyptians may know that i am
the lord
and they did so so what's happening here
pharaoh is going after the children
of israel he's hoping that they get
entangled in the wilderness reading on
verse 5 of exodus 14 it was told the
king of egypt that the people fled and
the heart of pharaoh
and of his servants was turned against
the people and they said
why have they done this that we have let
israel go
from serving us remember that word
those words serving us they were serving
in the house of bondage this is powerful
guys because what i want you to see here
is that pharaoh is coming after them
he's trying to bring them back to old
times
notice how the children of israel
respond when they
hear that pharaoh is coming after them
in exodus 14 verse 12 the children of
israel say this
is not this the word that we did tell
thee in egypt saying
let us alone that we may serve the
egyptians
you know i praise god that moses did not
leave the children of israel alone
i praise god children of israel thought
it would have been better
notice what it says for it had been
better for us to serve the egyptians
than that we should die in the
wilderness
catch this crucial point
the children of israel would have rather
served
than die they were afraid
of pharaoh they were afraid
of dying notice that in exodus 12 verse
we saw this month shall be unto you the
beginning of month it shall be the first
month of the year to you
so in a sense the passover marks the
beginning of something
the beginning of new times
however it also marks something else
because in exodus 14 13 the bible says
here and moses said unto the people
fear ye not stand still and see the
salvation of the lord which he will show
you today
for the egyptians who you have seen
today you shall
see them again no more
forever
all right guys watch this
in one sense god is saying the passover
marks
the beginning of something for you but
in another sense
it marks the ending of something for you
because when the children of israel in
exodus chapter 14 remember they're at
the red sea
they're at the where yes
the red sea when they're at the red sea
god is about to do
something that's going to bring an end
to something for them are you catching
this
this is to mark that what's about to
happen at the red sea
will mark the end of your
fear of your oppressor
so in a sense the passover represents
the beginning and also the
ending we might say
the alpha and the
yes yes yes i i think you are following
along so watch this guys
passover the beginning of something red
sea
the ending of something the beginning
and the ending and i want you to notice
this okay
because in exodus chapter 14 verse 24
verse 23 the bible says and the
egyptians pursued and went in after them
to the midst of the sea even all
pharaoh's horses
his chariots and his horsemen and it
came to pass
that in the morning watch
i just got a pause right there god would
say that it was between the three
o'clock and the six o'clock hour
of the morning it's in the morning watch
that the lord looked unto the host of
the egyptians through the pillar
of fire and cloud and troubled the hosts
of the egyptians moses stretched out his
hand over the sea
and the lord caused the sea to go back
by a strong
east wind all that night and made the
sea dry
and the waters were divided and the
children of israel went into the midst
of the sea upon the dry ground
and the waters were a wall unto them on
their right hand on there
and on their left so check this out guys
children are crossing the red sea
all night god has just performed a
miracle they have
crossed the red red sea and escaped
what was certain death the thought of
death must have been heavy upon them but
god does something miraculous
and brings them through and in the
morning
watch it is when the sea returns to its
strength
and the enemies of god's people are
swallowed up
in the morning early some speculate
that this was on the first day of the
week now
check this out guys what has god done to
the red sea
he parted the sea and now they're
walking through
changed nature
all of this beloved connected with the
passover and connected with the
red sea experience
it is after this that we get to the book
of exodus 15
and i want you to notice the children of
israel are now standing
on the opposite side of the shore and
the bible says here
then saying moses and the children of
israel this song unto the lord
he is my god and i will prepare him a
habitation
my father's god and i will exalt him now
watch this
the lord is a man of war
the lord is his name beloved it is after
this experience of the passover a lamb
being sacrificed the the red sea
experience
coming through what appears to be
certain death
that the children of israel now stand on
the opposite on the opposite shore
singing the song of moses
they are celebrating god
as a man of war they walked
through changed nature and now are
standing on the opposite shore
singing the song of moses and the lamb
it is in exodus 25
8. that the house of god is introduced
did you catch that let them make me a
sanctuary that i may dwell among them
the sanctuary is the house of god
watch this what has god done he has
led them through the passover and the
red sea experience
he has led them from the house of
bondage in which they served to the
house of
god which is a house of deliverance
in matthew chapter 2 verse 16 herod when
he saw that he was
mocked of the wise men was exceeding
roth and went forth
and slew all the children that were in
bethlehem and in all the coasts there
were from
two years old and under according to the
time which he had diligently inquired of
the wise men you remember this right
when jesus was born there was a death
decree just as there was a death decree
from moses
so there was a death decree in the time
of jesus
just as moses left egypt want you to
notice matthew chapter 2 14 when he
arose he took the young child this is
joseph and his mother
by night and departed into egypt and was
there until the death of herod that it
might be fulfilled which was saying
spoken of by the of the lord by the
prophet saying
out of egypt have i called my
son there's more because you remember
that the name moses means
drawn i'm go i'm getting to the to the
passover okay i'm getting to christ's
death burial and resurrection
so you just need to follow this remember
just as the name moses means drawn out
of water check this out
then jesus coming from galilee to jordan
unto john
to be baptized of him but john forbade
him saying i need to be baptized of thee
and cometh out to me and jesus answered
saying unto him
suffered be so for now then he suffered
them just as
moses was drawn out of waters to
accomplish submission
so jesus himself was baptized in
preparation for his mission
you remember that moses goes
into the wilderness for 40 years
just as jesus in matthew 4 verse 1 then
was jesus led up of the spirit
into the wilderness to be tempted of the
devil and when he had fasted how long
40 days and 40 nights he was afterward
of hunger jesus was in the wilderness
for 40
days as moses was in the wilderness for
years just as at the end of this time
moses
returns to begin to deliver his people
out of the house of bondage
so jesus returns out of the wilderness
to accomplish the very same thing but on
a
much larger scale
moses returns performing miracles
matthew 4 23
and jesus went about all galilee
teaching in their synagogues and
preaching the gospel of the kingdom
and healing all manner of sickness and
all manner of
disease among the people beloved what
i'm trying to tell you is that
what happened in exodus was a miniature
scale
of what would happen in the life of
jesus culminating with it with his
death burial and resurrection
escaping certain death
then we come to matthew chapter 26
where the bible says it came to pass
when jesus had finished all these things
he's selling to his disciples you know
that after two days is the feast of the
passover
and the son of man is betrayed to
be crucified you get this
are you catching this jesus
died on the passover
his death was to mark
the beginning oh man you're all not
feeling me
the death of jesus was specifically to
mark
the beginning of time for you and i
forget about
old times that's what the passover does
in john 14 verse 6. we want you to watch
this we know not with the thou goes
and how can we know the way john 14 6
jesus said i am the way
pause for a second
the greek word used here for the way
is the word hold us
u s h-o-d-u-s us
now i mean i need to just ask you but
what word does that
sound like to you hold us jesus says i
am the hodas
if you're thinking right now wait a
minute that sounds like exodus
you're right because that's where the
word comes the word
hold us means way or road so
x out of hold us the way that's what the
book that's what the title of the book
literally means
the way out jesus is saying
i am the hodas
i am the holdest ex the way
out the way out of what
the way out of the house
of bondage
through my death i provided you with a
new
beginning a new history a new
starting point this is why the bible
says in second corinthians 5 17
therefore if any man be in christ he is
a
new creature all things
are passed away behold all things are
become
new you you are actually experiencing
new beginnings
jesus is your
exodus now watch this his death
leads us away from the house of bondage
remember what egypt represents the house
of bondas
in romans chapter 7 verse 23 paul said
these words but i see
another law in my members
warring against the law of my mind and
bringing me into what
bringing me into captivity
yes guys yes bringing me into what
captivity to the law of sin
which is in my members oh wretched man
that i am
who shall deliver me from the body of
this death beloved
this was the house of bondage the flesh
all right look don't get me wrong
the old man is not going to let you
just leave freely
he's not going to let you leave without
a fight
pharaoh the old man is
not going to let you escape he's going
to want to try to bring you
back to old times
he's going to try to bring you back to
old times to always
to bring you back into the house of
bondage in fact
second peter chapter 2 verse 20 puts it
this way for if
after they have escaped the pollutions
of the world
through the knowledge of the lord and
savior jesus christ
and they are again entangled
that word entangled is only used only
three times in the scripture
one of them is when pharaoh says
i hope they get entangled in the
wilderness the other one
is right here
the old man wants to get us entangled
wants to get us entangled again in the
old ways
just as the children of israel went
through the red sea and it was in the
morning watch that the enemy was
defeated
so when jesus ascended from the grave
that sunday morning in the morning watch
the enemies that would draw us
back into the old ways
those enemies were defeated by the
resurrection
of jesus christ